<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ASPNet | dev/null]]></title>
  <link href="http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/blog/categories/aspnet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-07T23:23:43+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Graeme Christie]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET vNext on OSX and Linux Redux]]></title>
    <link href="http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/blog/2014/09/30/asp-dot-net-vnext-on-osx-and-linux-redux/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-30T22:13:57+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/blog/2014/09/30/asp-dot-net-vnext-on-osx-and-linux-redux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have changed a fair bit since my last post back in May, and getting the latest and greatest ASP.NET vNext up and running with Mono is now reasonably straight forward,
so I thought I&rsquo;d do a quick update on installing ASP.NET vNext on OSX and Linux.</p>

<h3>Install Mono</h3>

<p>Xamarin now maintains Mono packages for OSX and most common Linux distributions, and are committed to a regular release schedule, so getting Mono up and running is now a much simpler affair. Currently, there are supported packages for Mono. Installation is generally as simple as adding the Xamarin repository to your packages sources, and importing their GPG key) and then installing. I am going to cover OSX and Ubuntu 14.04 here, but easy instructions for most distros can be found <a href="http://www.mono-project.com/docs/getting-started/install/linux/.">http://www.mono-project.com/docs/getting-started/install/linux/.</a></p>

<h5>OSX</h5>

<ul>
<li>Simply download the Mono MDK from <a href="http://www.mono-project.com/download/#download-mac">http://www.mono-project.com/download/#download-mac</a> and run the installer.</li>
</ul>


<h5>Ubuntu 14.04</h5>

<ul>
<li>Add the Xamarin GPG key to apt
<code>
wget http://download.mono-project.com/repo/xamarin.gpg &amp;&amp; sudo apt-key add xamarin.gpg
</code></li>
<li>Add the Xamarin repository to apt
<code>
sudo sh -c 'echo "deb http://download.mono-project.com/repo/debian wheezy main" &gt; /etc/apt/sources.list.d/mono-xamarin.list'
</code></li>
<li>Update your package cache
<code>
sudo apt-get update
</code></li>
<li><p>Install the Mono development package
<code>
sudo apt-get install mono-devel
</code></p></li>
<li><p>We will need to install some certificates on Linux, to avoid getting an exception when downloading packages with nuget package restore. This is not required on OSX.
<code>
sudo certmgr -ssl -m https://go.microsoft.com
sudo certmgr -ssl -m https://nugetgallery.blob.core.windows.net
sudo certmgr -ssl -m https://nuget.org
mozroots --import --sync
</code></p></li>
</ul>


<h5>Check Your Mono Installation</h5>

<ul>
<li><p>Open a new shell and type <code>mono --version</code>. You should be running Mono version 3.8.0 or newer.</p>

<p>  <img src="https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/uploads-ap.hipchat.com/24631/1103057/CwcEnLnN2p3lZnh/upload.png" alt="Mono Version" /></p></li>
</ul>


<p>If not, you probably still have an old version of Mono on your path. This might be the case if you had previously installed Mono from source (as per my last blog post). You will want to make sure you remove your old installation. Running <code>make clean</code> from the Mono source code folder is probably the best way to do this. Additionally, remove any other installation that may have been installed via a third party package manager such as homebrew on OSX.</p>

<h3>Install KVM and the K Runtime</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>If your on Linux, you may need to install curl.
<code>
sudo apt-get install curl
</code>
<em>If you have any old (alpha) versions of kre installed, I recommend removing them from your system and starting fresh, and then starting a new shell. This will avoid any package sources being carried over in environment variables. I&rsquo;m not going to paste the commands here, for fear of people nuking their LOLcats image collection accidentally and blaming me .. but effectively you just want to remove the <code>~/.kre</code> folder from your home directory, and start a new shell.</em></p></li>
<li><p>Bootstrap your KVM installation by downloading and running the kvm install script from the <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/Home">aspnet/Home</a> respository. We are using the <code>dev</code> branch here, which will download a kvm that is pointing at the feed for the latest beta packages. At the time of writing the master branch is still pointing at the alpha CTP.
<code>
curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/aspnet/Home/dev/kvminstall.sh | sh &amp;&amp; source ~/.kre/kvm/kvm.sh
</code></p></li>
<li>Install the latest K Runtime
<code>
kvm upgrade
</code></li>
<li>Verify the latest install
<code>
kvm list
k --version
</code>
<img src="https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/uploads-ap.hipchat.com/24631/1103057/Me72unTWXm3RF85/upload.png" alt="KVM installed" /></li>
</ul>


<p>You should now have one of the latest betas installed. The active version from <code>kvm list</code> should reflect the actual version of kre that you see when you run <code>k --version</code>.</p>

<h3>Try out the Hello World vNext Demo from David Fowler&rsquo;s github repository</h3>

<p>David Fowler has created a Demo app for OSX and Linux, and put it up in his <a href="https://github.com/davidfowl/HelloWorldVNext">personal repository on GitHub</a>. To check everything is working properly, we are going to clone it, and run it locally on our OSX or Linux installation.</p>

<ul>
<li>First, install &ldquo;git&rdquo; if you don&rsquo;t already have it. OSX users can get it from <a href="http://git-scm.com/download/mac">git-scm.com</a>, or on Ubuntu
<code>
sudo apt-get-install git
</code></li>
<li>Clone the HelloWorldVNext repository
<code>
git clone https://github.com/davidfowl/HelloWorldVNext.git
</code></li>
<li>Navigate into the HelloWorldVNext directory
<code>
cd HelloWorldVNext
</code></li>
<li>Restore Packages
<code>
kpm restore
</code></li>
<li>Navigate to the src/helloworldweb directory
<code>
cd src/helloworldweb
</code></li>
<li>Run the web application
<code>
k web
</code></li>
<li><p>Open a browser and go to <a href="http://localhost:5000.">http://localhost:5000.</a> If everything is in order, you will see &ldquo;Hello World&rdquo; staring back at you &hellip;.</p>

<p><img src="https://jabbrlive.blob.core.windows.net/jabbr-uploads/clipboard_cf58.png" alt="Great Success" /></p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Final Notes</h3>

<p>The steps above are the bare minumum to get you up and running with vNext on Linux or OSX. The project is still (only barely) in beta, and is not ready the prime time yet. That being said, the ASP.NET vNext team at Microsoft have shown a huge commitment to cross platform support for the next iteration of ASP.NET. ASP.NET, running in production, on Linux, fully supported by Microsoft, <strong>will be a thing</strong>, and probably within the next twelve months. The time to get in there, get your hands dirty and kick the tires is now .. while the devs are ready and able to respond to your feedback.</p>

<p>If you have any problems or feedback, or just want to hang around and see what&rsquo;s going on, jump into the ASP.NET vNext chat channel at <a href="https://jabbr.net/#/rooms/AspNetvNext,">https://jabbr.net/#/rooms/AspNetvNext,</a> there is almost always someone around.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET vNext on OSX and Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/blog/2014/05/26/asp-dot-net-vnext-on-osx-and-linux/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T21:32:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graemechristie.github.com/graemechristie/blog/2014/05/26/asp-dot-net-vnext-on-osx-and-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>So what is ASP.NET vNext ?</h3>

<p>Microsoft have recently released a preview of the next iteration of their ASP.NET platform. I&rsquo;m not going to go into the details here, people like <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/IntroducingASPNETVNext.aspx">Scott Hanselman</a> have already done a fantastic job of that. I will however say that the changes, both technical and cultural, are huge. Two of those changes are particularly relevant to this blog post.</p>

<p>Firstly, ASP.NET vNext is fully open source. People like you and me are able to get in on the ground floor, try out the bits and pieces and even contribute &ndash;  pretty much from the project&rsquo;s inception.</p>

<p>Secondly, ASP.NET vNext is cross platform, and embraces non Windows hosts as first class citizens. Microsoft are fully integrating Mono and Linux into their build environment and test matrix, and are actively working with the community to make Mono a top class platform for hosting ASP.NET. That being said, these are early days, and the team is still ironing out issues with the Mono environment.</p>

<h3>Getting ASP.NET vNext up and running on OSX and Linux</h3>

<p>There are two main steps to getting to the point where we can run ASP.NET vNext applications on our non Windows system.</p>

<p>The first is to install Mono. Normally this would be a no brainer; however as all this stuff is very shiny and new there are fixes and features that are currently only in the bleeding edge source code of Mono and have not been released as a package as yet. In order to get these fixes we are going to need to build mono from the latest source code located in the mono git repository.</p>

<p>The second step is to install the &ldquo;K Runtime Environment&rdquo; or KRE. This is the command line environment that will build and run (not that there is really a distinction anymore) projects from their new project.json project files.</p>

<p>Installation of the KRE is handled by the &ldquo;K Version Manager&rdquo; (KVM). This is a simple app that can install multiple versions of the KRE side by side, and allow you to easily switch between them.</p>

<h3>Building Mono</h3>

<p>I don&rsquo;t want to go into too much detail here. There are plenty of <a href="http://www.mono-project.com/Compiling_Mono">guides around the internet</a> on installing mono from source.</p>

<ul>
<li>Install Mono as per the instructions at <a href="https://github.com/mono/mono">The Mono Github page</a>.</li>
<li>You will need an earlier mono release installed in order to build Mono from source (Mono uses Mono to build itself)</li>
<li>You will need autoconf, libtool and and a few other common dev tools installed on your system.</li>
<li>On some linux systems you may need to run the following before you run the mozroots command below.
<code>
sudo certmgr -ssl -m https://go.microsoft.com
sudo certmgr -ssl -m https://nugetgallery.blob.core.windows.net
sudo certmgr -ssl -m https://nuget.org
</code></li>
<li>If you are on linux, you will need to run <code>mozroots --import --sync</code> after installing mono to avoid certificate/trust issues down the line</li>
<li>If you are on OSX you will want to edit /private/etc/paths and move the line <code>/usr/local/bin</code> before the line <code>/usr/bin</code> so the system finds the new mono version on the path before the old one.</li>
</ul>


<p> <em>caveat: This may totally break your system if you have lots of crazy stuff in /usr/local/bin. If your not sure about this, wait for a supported official release of Mono</em></p>

<p>Once all this is done, run <code>mono --version</code>. You should see that you are running Mono version 3.4.1 or newer.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/uploads-ap.hipchat.com/36968/482094/fPMtOGUiN1vyLzx/upload.png" alt="mono --version" /></p>

<p>If you do not, check your <code>$PATH</code> variable and go back over the mono install steps.</p>

<h3>Installing KVM and the K Runtime Environment</h3>

<p>Installing KVM is super simple. If you like you can go to the <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/Home#osxlinux">Readme for the AspNet Home project</a> and follow the &ldquo;Getting Started&rdquo; instructions there, however that involves cloning the Home Repository which is only required for that quick start demo.</p>

<p>KVM can be installed on any Linux or OSX system (that has bash or zsh and curl installed) with a single line.</p>

<p><code>
curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/aspnet/Home/master/kvminstall.sh | sh &amp;&amp; source ~/.kre/kvm/kvm.sh &amp;&amp; kvm upgrade
</code></p>

<p>This will:</p>

<ul>
<li>download kvm.sh and save it in ~/.kre/kvm/kvm.sh</li>
<li>add the command to run kvm.sh on every login to bash/zsh.</li>
<li>kvm.sh will then be run via the <code>source</code> command. This adds the <code>kvm</code> command to the current shell.</li>
<li>run <code>kvm upgrade</code>. This will download the latest KRE package, extract it to .kre/packages and add the bin folder to your path.</li>
</ul>


<p>Once this is done, all of the KRE commands will be available from shell prompt. Primarily this will be the <code>k</code> command used to run ASP.NET vNext Projects, and the <code>kpm</code> command used to restore packages.</p>

<p>Additionally the kvm command can be used to install other version of KRE side by side for the user, switch between versions, list the installed versions and set up aliases. See the <a href="https://github.com/aspnet/Home#running-the-samples">ASP.NET Home Project Readme</a> for examples of the various <code>kvm</code> commands.</p>

<h3>Okay, so I&rsquo;ve got a Shiny New KRE &hellip;.</h3>

<p>So let&rsquo;s point it at something. We could download one of the many samples from the aspnet repository, however just to prove we have everything we need to build and run ASP.NET vNext apps on OSX and Linux, lets create a very basic project from scratch.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Create a folder called <em>HelloKRuntime</em> somewhere on your system and <code>cd</code> into that folder</p></li>
<li><p>Create a file called <code>project.json</code> and copy the following text into it. This is your ASP.NET vNext project file .. and not an angle bracket to be seen !
<code>json
{
  "dependencies": {
    "System.Console": "4.0.0.0"
  },
  "configurations": {
    "net45": {},
    "k10": {}
  }
}
</code></p></li>
<li><p>Create a file called Program.cs and copy the following text into it.
```aspx-cs
using System;</p>

<p>public class Program
{
    public static void Main()
    {
        Console.WriteLine(&ldquo;Hello K Runtime !&rdquo;);
    }
}
```</p></li>
<li><p>type <code>kpm restore -s https://www.myget.org/F/aspnetvnext/</code>
The K Package Manager will head off to the nuget repository and fetch <code>System.Console</code> and all its dependencies, based on the entry in your project.json file. Note that there is no need to use Nuget to install this package. The project.json entry is all the info kpm needs to fetch your dependencies.</p></li>
</ul>


<p> <em>Note: Because the ASP.NET vNext project is currently using their own nuget feed, we need to supply the nuget source on the command line. This can be provided in a NuGet.Config file in your Solution folder, and once the vNext is released you shouldn&rsquo;t need one at all unless you are using your own private nuget feeds.</em></p>

<p> <img src="https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/uploads-ap.hipchat.com/36968/482094/VORbSwiBWtopBnQ/upload.png" alt="kpm restore" /></p>

<ul>
<li>Now type <code>k run</code> from the command line. You should see your system burst to life and utter those immortal words</li>
</ul>


<p> <img src="https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/uploads-ap.hipchat.com/36968/482094/tAex4VvNajwBtUS/upload.png" alt="Hello K Runtime" /></p>

<ul>
<li>As an example of how the new Configuration system ties into the environment, try typing <code>export KRE_TRACE=1</code> and then <code>k run</code> again. You will see the compiler output as well as the &ldquo;Hello K Runtime&rdquo; message.</li>
</ul>


<p> <img src="https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/uploads-ap.hipchat.com/36968/482094/iSZ9yKiAaxzlWdO/upload.png" alt="Hello Compiler Output" /></p>

<h3>In Summary</h3>

<p>Hopefully this post has demonstrated that cross platform ASP.NET vNext functionality is available now. There are still rough edges, but progress is being made daily and first class support for OSX and Linux environments is on the horizon. If you are having issues getting this working, feel free to drop into the <a href="https://jabbr.net/#/rooms/AspNetvNext">aspnetvnext room on Jabbr</a> and someone should be able to help you out.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE: If you&rsquo;d like to try something more involved than the trivial console application above, the simple <a href="https://github.com/davidfowl/HelloWorldVNext">Hello World V Next</a> web example might be a good next step.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
